Guide to the Laurent Clerc Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Laurent Clerc papers
1811-1896
MS 140
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
The papers consist of correspondence relating to the founding of the American School for the Deaf and Dumb in Hartford, Connecticut in 1817 by Laurent Clerc at the invitation of Thomas H. Gallaudet. Included also is a diary in English kept by Clerc during his voyage to the United States from France (1816) together with transcriptions of newspaper accounts of his first address in the United States, newspaper clippings, legal and financial documents, student papers, and memorabilia. There are a few family and personal papers and autobiographical notes by Clerc (1857-1869). Principal correspondents are John Louis Cheverus, Thomas H. Gallaudet, Abbé Sicard, and Roberts Vaux.
Clerc, Laurent, 1785-1869
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Guy B. Holt, 1962.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Selected correspondence and other writings from the Laurent Clerc Papers are available on microfilm (405 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM77. This film also includes selected items from the Silliman Family Papers (MS 450) and eighty-three items from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two chronological sequences, the first consisting of correspondence and the second of all other material.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence relating to the founding of the American School for the Deaf and Dumb in Hartford, Connecticut in 1817 by Laurent Clerc at the invitation of Thomas H. Gallaudet. Included also is a diary in English kept by Clerc during his voyage to the United States from France (1816) together with transcriptions of newspaper accounts of his first address in the United States, newspaper clippings, legal and financial documents, student papers, and memorabilia. There are a few family and personal papers and autobiographical notes by Clerc (1857-1869). Principal correspondents are John Louis Cheverus, Thomas H. Gallaudet, Abbé Sicard, and Roberts Vaux.
Biographical / Historical
Laurent Clerc became deaf at the age of one year. He was educated at the Institute for the Deaf and Dumb in Paris, where he became a teacher in 1805. In 1816 he joined Thomas Hopkins Gallaudet in founding the American School for the Deaf and Dumb in Hartford, Connecticut, where he taught until 1858.
Deaf -- Education and institutions; Education; French -- United States; Shipping; Europe; Diaries; Educators; Cheverus, Jean-Louis-Anne-Madeleine Lefebvre de, 1768-1836; Clerc, Laurent, 1785-1869; Gallaudet, T. H. (Thomas Hopkins), 1787-1851; Sicard, Roch Ambroise, 1742-1822; Vaux, Roberts, 1786-1836; American School, at Hartford, for the Deaf
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - [Abbé Ambroise Sicard to [ _____ ]?, [1804 August 18?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Laurent Clerc to his parents, [1805 August 11?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [ _____ ] Gard to Laurent Clerc, 1811 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Laurine Duler to Laurent Clerc, 1812 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Laurent Clerc to Abbé Sicard [draft of pupil's address to Sicard], 1812 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [Laurent Clerc] to [ _____ ], 1813 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Laurent Clerc to [ _____ ] Langlois, 1815 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Abbé Sicard to Laurent Clerc (2 items), 1816 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Laurent Clerc's Communion Class to their teacher, 1816 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Laurent Clerc (for the Instructors) to the Administrators, 1816 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Laurent Clerc to the Administrators, [ca, 1816 May 10] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - (Mrs.) Gouin to [Laurent Clerc?], 1816 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Abbé Sicard to Bishop John Cheverus (2 items), 1816 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bishop John Cheverus to Laurent Clerc, 1816 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bishop John Cheverus to Enoch Fenwick, 1816 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bishop John Cheverus to W. Matthews, 1816 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - H.Bleecher to John Randolph, 1816 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - [Abbé Sicard to Laurent Clerc?], [1816?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Laurent Clerc to Abbé Sicard Abbé Sicard to Laurent Clerc (2 items), [1816?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - J. Robertson to Laurent Clerc, [1816?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - [Joseph] J. Corre to Laurent Clerc?], 1817 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Abbé Sicard to Laurent Clerc, 1817 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - [ _____ ] to [ _____ ] Massieu, 1818 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - [N. Crocker?] to Laurent Clerc, 1819 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Eliza C. (Mrs. Laurent) Clerc to Laurent Clerc, 1819 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Alice Cogswell to Laurent Clerc, 1819 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - [[ _____ ] Bessefines?] to Laurent Clerc, 1820 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Caroline Chester to Laurent Clerc, 1820 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Laurent Clerc to Benjamin Prescott, [1820 December 18?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Roberts Vaux to Laurent Clerc, 1822 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Laurent Clerc to Roberts Vaux, 1822 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Laurent Clerc to John C. Spencer, 1827 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - [[ _____ ] Cassolis?] to Laurent Clerc, [1833 September 19?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Laurent Clerc to F.A.P. Barnard, 1835 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Francis J. (Francois) Clerc to his mother, Eliza C. (Mrs. Laurent) Clerc, 1836 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Carlin to [ _____ ] Allabough, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - E. Booth to Francis J. Clerc (2 items), 1886 February 23, March 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Francis J. Clerc to Dr. [ _____ ] Peet, 1890 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - [Job Turner?] to Francis J. Clerc, 1895 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Excerpt from Journal de Paris re the Comet, 1811 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Massieu's?] commendation of Institute Alumni, [1812?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Abbé Sicard on discipline, [1812-1815?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Petition to the Emperor, on behalf of deaf-mutes and Abbé Sicard, [1812-1815?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A joke on Laurent Clerc, [1812-1815?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Program of lectures by Abbé Sicard on deaf-mutes, in London (with notes from lecture sessions), 1815 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - List of dinner guests, [1815 June-Jul?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Certificate of departure from England for Laurent Clerc, 1815 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Laurent Clerc's copy of a letter from Abbé Sicard to a friend, re post-Waterloo political situation?], [1815-1816?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Contract between Laurent Clerc and Thomas H. Gallaudet, appointing Clerc as instructor in Gallaudet's proposed Hartford institute for the deaf and dumb, 1816 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lists of pupils of Laurent Clerc, 1817-1819 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter of commendation of Laurent Clerc by French envoy to the United States, 1819 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Contract renewing Laurent Clerc's appointment at Hartford American Asylum, 1820 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Transcript of conversation between Abbé Sicard and [ _____ ], 1820 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Copy of court record granting Laurent Clerc residency rights in Connecticut, 1827 January (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Laurent Clerc's passport, 1835 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Hints to Teachers of the Deaf and Dumb", [1851] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Will of Marie Clerc, Laurent Clerc's sister, 1856 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Petition of deaf-mute alumni for a pension for Laurent Clerc, 1856 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Autobiographical notes by Laurent Clerc, with photograph, [1857-1869?] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notes prepared [by Francis J. Clerc] "for use, at the Centennial of Clerc's birth, in Philadelphia, but not used", 1885 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Petition of deaf-mute artist A. Aubert to, Minister of State, for a grant to travel to Rome, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Report by Laurent Clerc to Minister of State, on teaching of deaf-mutes, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes on teaching of deaf-mutes [by Laurent Clerc?], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Note on teaching of Bible, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fragment of personal agenda, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Card of Laffitte, Gaillard & Cie (Stagecoaches and trains), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings and announcements
    - [Burlington]: visit of Thomas Gallaudet and Laurent Clerc, 1816 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [New York and Boston Youth's Cabinet ]: "American Asylum for the Deaf and Dumb of Hartford, Ct.", 1840 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [ Hartford Daily Courant ]: "Great Meeting of Deaf-Mutes", 1850 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [St. Louis]: "Distinguished Arrival" [of Laurent Clerc on a visit to St. Louis], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [ _____ ]: "L'Epee, Teacher of the Deaf and Dumb", undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Excerpts copied by Laurent Clerc from newspaper articles on his work and "addresses", 1816 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Laurent Clerc's diary of trip to America (2 copies), 1816 June 18-August 8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Francis J. Clerc: partial listing of the Laurent Clerc Papers, 1874, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 18)